为时六周的课程就要完结了。我这门课讲的很愉悦
This brings us to the end of the six weeks
course. I had a lot of fun teaching this
希望大家也是。我非常喜欢课程的内容
course and I hope you enjoyed it too. I
really love this material and I always
也总是乐意讲授它。在说再见之前，先快速回顾一下
enjoy teaching it. Before we say our
farewells, please do a quick review of the
我们讨论过的话题，看看还剩下什么东西没讲
topics that we discussed and see what's
left to cover. So here's a brief diagram
这是一个我们已经讨论过的密码学原型的简要图示。
如果大家还记得在第一周里
of the primitive that we discussed in the
class. If you remember in week one we
我们从伪随机数发生器和流密码开始讨论
started off by discussing pseudorandom
generators and stream ciphers. In week two
第二周我们讨论了分组密码，我们说过正确的思考
we talked about block ciphers and we said
that the right way to think about block
分组密码的方式是当作伪随机置换和伪随机函数
cipher is as pseudorandom permutations and
pseudorandom functions. We said that using
我们说过，通过使用计数器模式，我们可以把一个
分组密码转换成一个PRG。我们说过，使用GGM机制
counter mode we can convert a block cipher
into a PRG. And we said that using the GGM
我们可以从伪随机发生器构建分组密码
construction. We can construct block
ciphers from pseudorandom generators. Then
然后在第三周，我们讨论了数据完整性
in week three, we talked about data
integrity. In particular, we talked about
特别地，我们讨论了MAC，看了各种MAC机制
MACs and we looked at various
constructions of MACs from pseudorandom
它们是基于伪随机函数，比如CMAC，HMAC，PMAC等等
functions like the CMAC, the HMAC, the
PMAC constructions and so on. We also
我们还讨论了抗碰撞，我们说过抗碰撞可以被用来
discussed collision resistance and we said
that collision resistance can be used for
保护数据完整性，当有只读内存的访问权限时
data integrity where one has access to
read-only memory. Basically, you would
你可以使用抗碰撞的哈希函数计算数据的哈希值
hash the data using a collision resistance
hash function; write the hash into
向只读内存写哈希值。稍后当你想验证你的数据时
read-only memory. And then later, when you
want to verify authenticity of your data,
你只需比较它的哈希值和写在只读内存里的数据
you just compare its hash to whatever is
written in read-only memory. Then in week 4
那么在第四周，我们讨论了如何把完整性和私密性结合起来
we talked about how to combine integrity
and confidentiality, in particular we
特别地，我们讨论了把加密和MAC结合起来，以构建
kinda talk about to combine encryption and
MACs to build what we called Authenticated
所谓的认证加密。我告诉过大家，在实际中
Encryption and I told you that really in
practice, the only foremost Symmetric
在对称加密中，你们只能使用认证加密
Encryption that you're allowed to use is
Authenticated Encryption. Basically,
只对窃听保持安全的加密通常是不安全的
encryption that's only secure against
eavesdropping attacks is not generally
大家必须时时刻刻提防数据被篡改，因此
secure, you must always also guard against
tampering and as a result, you should only
大家应当只使用认证加密模式，来进行对称加密
be using Authenticated Encryption modes to
do Symmetric Encryption. So that was the
那么这是第四周。第五周和第六周中，我们转变了话题
end of week four. And then for weeks five
and six, we switched topics and talked
讨论了密钥交换和公钥加密。特别地，在第五周
about key exchange and public key encryption.
In particular, in week five we talked
我们讨论了陷门函数和Diffie-Hellman协议
about Trapdoor Functions and the
Diffie-Hellman Protocol within the
还有为了解释这些东西如何工作的必要的数学
Mathematics that are necessary to explain
how those things work. And then in week
然后在第六周，我们讨论了如何从陷门函数
six we talked about how public key encryption
can be built from trapdoor functions and,
和Diffie-Hellman协议构建公钥加密。
我想强调一下，我们在第五周看到的
the Diffie-Hellman Protocol. I wanna
emphasize that the key exchange protocols
密钥交换协议只能安全地抵抗窃听攻击
that we saw in week five are only secure
against eavesdropping and should never be
在实际中永远不应该被使用。事实上在第八周
我们将看到认证密钥交换协议
used in practice. In fact in week eight
we're gonna see authenticated key exchange
那些是在现实中实际被使用的
protocols and those are the ones that are
actually used in the world for example in
例如在SSL以及其他类似协议中。但是，我们在第五周
SSL and other protocols like that. But,
the ones that we saw in week five should
看到的内容，在实际中永远不应该被使用的。
我们看这些简单密钥交换机制的原因
never actually be deployed in the real
world. The only reason we looked at those
只是为了给陷门函数和Diffie-Hellman群做铺垫
simple key exchange mechanisms was as
motivation for trapdoor functions and
现在如你所知，我们整个密码学课程还有四周
Diffie-Hellman groups. Now as you know there
are four more weeks to the full crypto
我们以后还要上四周。在第七周我们将讨论
course which we're gonna do at a later
time. In week seven we're gonna talk about
数字签名，以及如何认证数据，使得每个人
digital signatures and how to authenticate
data in a way that anyone can verify that
都能认证数据的真实性。然后我们讨论认证密钥交换协议
the data is authentic. Then we're gonna
talk about authenticated key exchanges as
如我所说的。然后我们将讨论用户认证，如何管理口令
I said then we're gonna talk about user
authentication, how to manage passwords,
一次性口令，挑战-应答协议，然后我们讨论
one time passwords, challenge-response
protocols. Then we'll talk about various
各种隐私机制。如何认证自己，同时又不会暴露自己身份？
privacy mechanisms. How to authenticate
yourself without revealing where you are,
如何在登录的同时，不会暴露自己是谁等等。。
How to sign in a way it doesn't reveal who
you are and so on and so forth. And in this part
在这一部分里，为这些机制构建分组，实际上
of the building blocks for some of these
mechanisms, actually, we'll talk about
我们将讨论零知识证明，这是一个通用的工具
zero-knowledge protocols which is kind of
a general purpose tool that's used very
在密码学中广泛使用。但是其实密码学已经超越了
widely in cryptography. But let's just say
that crypto goes way beyond this core
这个基本内容，事实上还有很多话题我想跟大家说
topics and in fact, there are many, many
more topics that I would love to tell you
如果时间允许的话。那么我制作了这张简短的表
about if there was enough time. So I made
this kind of a short list here and this isn't
这张表并不完全。还有很多其他内容我想跟大家讨论
even an exhaustive list. There are many
other things that I would like to tell you
那么如果反响够强，我可以开一门高等密码学课程
about and so if there's enough demand, I
might even run an advanced crypto class
通常是我给研究生上的
which is usually what I do for graduate
students which would cover these more
会涵盖更多的高级话题，但那将是明年的事了
advanced topics but that would actually
take place sometime next year so stay
所以不要走开，当做出决定时，我会给出通知
tuned and I will send announcements on
when that's coming. So my final words of
当然，我对本课的最后几句话是：密码学是强大的工具
course remember my main message from this
class. And that crypto is a tremendous
但是大家使用它时，应时刻小心谨慎
tool but you should always be careful when
you use it. If you implement crypto
如果你错误地实现了密码，系统也会正常运行
incorrectly, the system will work
perfectly fine. It would be no way to
无从判断其安全性，除非攻击者蓄意攻击系统时
tell that anything is wrong except when
attacker is trying to attack the system,
它将被轻易破解。所以密码学里
it might be easily breakable. And so
crypto is one of these things where a
一丁点知识都可能是危险的
little bit of knowledge is quite
dangerous. It's quite important to make
确保正确的实现是很重要的，一种确保的方法是
sure you get the implementation correctly
and one way to do that is to make sure
总是让别人来审查你的代码和设计
that always other people review your code
and your designs to find any bugs in the
找出密码实现里的漏洞，甚至是设计层面的更一般的漏洞
crypto implementation or even more general
bugs in the system design. And finally
最后我留给大家这些结束语：大家永远不要
I'll leave you with these parting words, that you should never ever invent your own
自己发明密码，也不要去实现自己的密码和模式
ciphers or your own modes and you should
never even implement your own ciphers or
尽可能地坚持使用标准
your own modes. Try to stick to the
standards as much as possible. Try to
尽可能地坚持使用算法的标准实现
stick to standard implementations of those
algorithms as much as possible and if you
如果万不得已，那么要确保你的工作有充分的
have to deviate from that, then just make
sure there's sufficient third party review
第三方审查。好，那么我这里先说再见了
of what you've done. Okay, so I will
say my farewell here. And let me say that
告诉大家，期终考试将在第七周上线
the final exam will be made available on
week seven, basically, a week after the
第六周后一周，所有讲座将向公众开放。
期终考试将涵盖六周的全部内容
week six lectures become public. The final
exam will cover material for all six weeks
它和问题集的格式差不多
and it'll pretty much be the same format
as the problem sets. I hope everybody will
我希望大家在考试中都能做得很好，当工作完成后可以领证书
do well in the exam and we will send
certificates once all those course work is
我希望在本课程的第二季里看到大家
complete and I hope to see you in the next
iteration of this course whenever that's
那么该说再见了，请在论坛里提交你们的
made available. So farewell, and as
always, please submit your comments and
评论和建议，我读了大家所有的评论，
它们对于改善本课程很有帮助
suggestions on the forum. I read all of
your posts and they're very, very helpful
希望在这个秋天还能见到大家
in improving the course. Hope to see you
in the fall.